#### Curriculum Vitae

# **Erlend Dancke Sandorf**

#### **Personal Information**

Date of birth: 11-08-1987 Nationality: Norwegian

E-mail: erlend.dancke.sandorf@slu.se

Telephone: +47 412 11 452

Languages: Norwegian (native), English (fluent), German (basic)

Orcid ID: orcid.org/0000-0001-7521-4773

Website: https://edsandorf.me

### Research interests and expertise

My research focuses on non-market valuation of ecosystem services. In particular, the use of advanced discrete choice models to accommodate non-utility maximizing behavior, and the use of simplifying strategies and heuristics. I have developed and utilized models that consider simplifying strategies such as attribute non-attendance, elimination-by-aspects and satisficing.

Software expertise: Ox, R, Matlab, NGENE, LaTeX, Microsoft Office.

${f E}$	a	16	'n	ŤΤ		n
1	u	шv	a	u	w	и

Education	
2012 - 2016	PhD Environmental and Resource Economics
	UiT - The Arctic University of Norway, Faculty of Biosciences,
	Fisheries and Economics, The Norwegian College of Fishery Science
	Thesis: "Valuing Unfamiliar and Complex Ecosystem Services – The Influence of Survey Mode, Knowledge and Dishonesty"
2010 - 2012	MSc Business Administration
	The Norwegian University of Life Sciences, School of Economics and
	Business
	Thesis: "Recycling as a Private Contribution to a Public Good: The
	Effect of Consistent and Inconsistent Information on the Recycling Decision"
	Major: Environmental and Resource Economics
	Minor: Leadership and Organization
2007 - 2010	BSc Business Administration
	The Norwegian University of Life Sciences, School of Economics and
	Business

Curre	nt Pa	sition

<b>Current Position</b>	
2016 – present	Postdoctoral Researcher
	Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences, Department of Forest
	Economics, Centre for Environmental and Resource Economics, Umeå,
	Sweden
<b>Previous Positions</b>	
2012 - 2016	PhD Candidate
	UiT - The Arctic University of Norway, Faculty of Biosciences,
	Fisheries and Economics, The Norwegian College of Fishery Science
Publications	
Publications in peer-	reviewed scientific journals
6.	Sandorf, E. D. & Campbell, D., 2018, Accommodating Satisficing
	Behavior in Stated Choice Experiments, European Review of
	Agricultural Economics, forthcoming
5.	Daniel, A. M., Persson, L. & Sandorf, E. D., 2018, Accounting for
	Elimination-by-Aspects Strategies and Demand Management in
	Electricity Contract Choice, Energy Economics, 73:80-90
4.	Sandorf, E. D., Crastes dit Sourd, R. & Mahieu, PA., 2018, Left to
	right – line by line: The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays
	on preferences and processing strategies, <u>Journal of Choice Modelling</u> ,
	in press
3.	Xuan, B. B., Sandorf, E. D. & Aanesen, M., 2017, Informing
	Management Strategies for a Reserve: Results from a Discrete Choice
	Experiment Survey, Ocean and Coastal Management, 145:35-43
2.	Sandorf, E. D., Campbell, D. & Hanley, N., 2016, Disentangling the
	Influence of Knowledge on Attribute Non-Attendance, Journal of
	Choice Modelling, 24:36-50
1.	Sandorf, E. D., Aanesen, M. & Navrud, S., 2016, Valuing Unfamiliar
	and Complex Environmental Goods: A Comparison of Valuation
	Workshops and Internet Panel Surveys with Videos, Ecological
	Economics, 129:50-61
Working papers and	papers currently under review
2.	Sandorf, E. D., 2016, Did You Miss Something? Inattentive
	Respondents in Discrete Choice Experiments

2.	Sandorf,	Ε.	<b>D.</b> ,	2016,	Did	You	Miss	Something?	Inattentive
	Responde	nts i	n Dis	screte C	hoice	Exper	iments		

1. Armstrong, C. W., Aanesen, M., van Rensburg, T. M. & Sandorf, E. D., 2016, It's the Ecology, Stupid - An Economic Argument for Inclusive Ocean Governance

### **Awards and Honors**

20	1	7
2υ	1	/

Best paper award for "The effect of attribute – alternative matrix displays on preferences and processing strategies" at the Workshop on Non-Market Valuation (WONV) in Leeds, UK.

### **Invited presentations**

211 ( 100 to P 1 0 5 0 11 10 11 5 11 5	
2018	Invite Seminar, Technical University of Delft, 14 <sup>th</sup> of June
	Presentation: "Satisficing in discrete choice experiments - some
	possibilities"
2018	Invited Seminar, Berlin DCE Colloquium 16, Technical University of
	Berlin, 12 <sup>th</sup> of June
	Presentation: "Incorporating non-RUM decision rules into the analysis
	of discrete choice experiments
2018	Invited Seminar, University of Nantes, LEMNA, 15th of March
	Presentation: "The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on
	preferences and processing strategies"
2018	Invited Seminar, University of Leeds, 8 <sup>th</sup> of February
2010	Presentation: "Assessing the impact of 'professional' respondents using
	an Integrated Choice and Latent Variable model"
	an integrated choice and Latent , artable model
2017	Invited Seminar, University of Gothenburg, 27 <sup>th</sup> of March
	Presentation: "Trapped! Catching inattentive respondents in an online
	discrete choice experiment"
	•

# **Conference and Workshop Presentations (past 5 years)**

2018	6 <sup>th</sup> World Congress for Environmental and Resource Economists, University of Gothenburg, Gothenburg, Sweden, 25 <sup>th</sup> – 29 <sup>th</sup> of June Presentation: "Assessing the impact of 'professional' respondents using an integrated choice and latent variable model"
2018	25 <sup>th</sup> Ulvön Conference on Environmental Economics, Ulvön, Sweden, 19 <sup>th</sup> – 21 <sup>st</sup> of June  Presentation: "Assessing the impact of 'professional' respondents using
	an integrated choice and latent variable model"
2017	ENVECHO VI Workshop, University of Bern, Bern, Switzerland, $25^{th}$ – $26^{th}$ of September
	Presentation: "The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on preferences and processing strategies"

2017	Workshop on Non-Market Valuation (WONV), University of Leeds, Leeds, United Kingdom, $26^{th}-27^{th}$ of June Presentation: "The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on preferences and processing strategies"
2017	$24^{th}$ Ulvön Conference on Environmental Economics, Ulvön, Sweden, $20^{th}-22^{nd}$ of June Presentation: "The effect of attribute-alternative matrix displays on preferences and processing strategies"
2017	International Choice Modeling Conference (ICMC), University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa, 3 <sup>rd</sup> – 5 <sup>th</sup> of April Presentation: "That's good enough! Satisficing in Stated Choice Experiments"
2016	Workshop on Non-Market Valuation (WONV), Bordeaux, France, 20 <sup>th</sup> – 21 <sup>st</sup> of June Presentation: "Dishonest Respondents in Discrete Choice Experiments – An Example using a Probability Based Internet Panel"
2016	Experiments for Environmental Policy Formation Conference, University of Stirling, Stirling, United Kingdom, 14 <sup>th</sup> of April Presentation: "Dishonest Respondents in Discrete Choice Experiments – An Example using a Probability Based Internet Panel"
2016	Annual Meeting of the Norwegian Association of Economists, Norwegian University of Science and Technology, $4^{th}-5^{th}$ of January Presentation: "Dishonest Respondents in Discrete Choice Experiments – An Example using an Internet Panel
2015	Annual Conference of the European Association of Environmental and Resource Economists (EAERE), University of Helsinki, Finland, 24 <sup>th</sup> – 25 <sup>th</sup> of June  Presentation: "Disentangling the Influence of Knowledge on Processing Strategies in Discrete Choice Modeling"  Poster: "Novel Survey Modes for Valuing Unfamiliar and Complex Environmental Goods: Valuation Workshops versus Internet Panel Surveys with Videos"
2015	International Choice Modeling Conference (ICMC), University of Texas, Austin, TX, USA, $10^{th} - 13^{th}$ of May Presentation: "Disentangling the Influence of Knowledge on Processing Strategies in Choice Modeling"

2015	Annual Meeting of the Norwegian Association of Economists, University of Bergen, Bergen, Norway, $5^{th} - 6^{th}$ of January Presentation: "Survey Mode Effects: Comparing Valuation Workshops and an Online Panel"
2014	Scottish Choice Modelling Conference, University of Stirling, Stirling, United Kingdom 16 <sup>th</sup> of October Presentation: "Mode Effects: Valuation Workshops versus Online Panels"
2014	Annual BIOECON Conference, Kings College, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, United Kingdom, $21^{st} - 23^{rd}$ of September Presentation: "Reliable Estimates? Evidence from a Discrete Choice Experiment on Cold Water Corals in Norway"
2014	International Conference of the International Institute of Fisheries Economics and Trade (IIFET), Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Australia, 7 <sup>th</sup> – 11 <sup>th</sup> of July Presentation: "Exploring Discontinuous Preferences in Discrete Choice Experiments: The Case of Cold-Water Corals in Norway"

# Academic Visits (1 week or longer)

2018	Visiting researcher (4 weeks)
	Technical University of Delft, Transport and Logistics Group, The
	Netherlands
	Host: Professor Caspar Chorus
2018	Visiting researcher (3 weeks)
	University of Leeds, Institute for Transport Studies, Leeds, United
	Kingdom
	Host: Professor Stephane Hess
2014	Visiting PhD Candidate (3 months)
	University of St. Andrews, St. Andrews, Scotland
	Host: Professor Nick Hanley
2009 - 2010	International Exchange Program (10 months)
	Montana State University, Bozeman, MT, USA

# **Grants and Funding**

2018 Producer and consumer preferences for sustainable shrimp aquaculture policy in Vietnam (NAFOSTED project nr. 502.99-2018.25) – 2018 – 2020 – Co-applicant – Total amount: \$28,000

2015	Travel	Grant

NOK 30 000 from the Research Council of Norway to participate in the Emerging Leaders Program during the Arctic Frontiers 2015 conference. The selected candidates participated in a mix of technical, social and cultural events accompanied by mentors from business, politics and academia on issues related to the Arctic.

### **Teaching Experience**

O .						
2017 - present	Lecturer, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences					
	PhD course: SPF – 0016 – Stated Preference Methods: State of the Art					
	Modeling (9 class room hours + seminars)					
	BSc course: SKO151 – Forest Economics (12 class room hours)					
2013 - 2015	Teaching Assistant, UiT – The Arctic University of Norway					
	MSc course: SOK - 3002 Advance Natural Resource Economics					
	BSc course: SOK - 2037 Resource Economics					
	BSc course: SOK - 2005 Economics II					
	BSc course: SOK - 1102 Economics I					
2011	Teaching Assistant, The Norwegian University of Life Sciences					
	BSc course: ECN - 210 Microeconomics					
	BSc course: ECN - 211 Microeconomics II					

### **Institutional Responsibilities and Professional Roles**

2013 - 2016	Norwegian Delegate						
	European Council of Doctoral Candidates and Junior Researchers (EURODOC)						
2013 - 2016	Board Member Association of Doctoral Organizations in Norway (Stipendiatorganisasjonene i Norge, SiN)						
2013-2014	Board Chair Tramed Destarel Students (TODOS)						
	Tromsø Doctoral Students (TODOS)						

### Membership of Scientific Societies and Organizations

2015 - present	European	Association	of	Environmental	and	Resource	Economists
	(EAERE)						

### **Reviewing Activities**

Agribusiness; Environmental and Resource Economics; European Review of Agricultural Economics; Journal of Choice Modelling; Journal of Environmental Economics and Management; Journal of Forest Economics